Guide to the Than Vanneman Ranck Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Than Vanneman Ranck papers
1916-1947
MS 1432
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.25
(15 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, cables, and telegrams which document Than Vanneman Ranck's service as editorial manager for the Hearst newspapers from 1928 to 1937. The papers highlight Ranck's role as editor of the "March of Events" section, a Sunday supplement to which prominent world leaders contributed. Also included are files concerning feature stories which Ranck secured for the Hearst chain, especially on Arctic and Antarctic exploration and pioneering aeronautical flights.
Ranck, Than Vanneman, 1874-1947
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Doris Rend, 1985.
Arrangement
Arranged in alphabetical order by topic and/or correspondent.
Scope and Contents
The Than Vanneman Ranck Papers consist of Ranck's files as editorial manager for William Randolph Hearst's chain of newspapers from 1928 to 1937. The papers highlight Ranck's role as editor of the "March of Events" section and his efforts to secure feature stories concerning Arctic and Antarctic explorations and pioneering aeronautical flights. Doris Rend, Ranck's daughter, donated the papers to the Yale University Library in 1985.
The files are arranged alphabetically by topic and include correspondence, telegrams, cables, and occasionally manuscripts for articles. The primary correspondents are members of the Hearst organization: William Randolph Hearst; Frank Knox and Thomas White, the general managers; and foreign correspondents or Berlin, London and Rome bureau heads William Hillman, Valerio Pignatelli, Karl von Wiegand, Robert J. Prew, and Robert Wells Ritchie. Correspondence with these individuals and the bureaus concerns the range of story topics and contains evaluations of a story's newsworthiness, details of finance and contract negotiations, and policy on publishing and marketing various features. The Hearst correspondence in particular illustrates the degree of control exercised by William Randolph Hearst in directing content and overseeing details of finance to shape the character of his papers.
When Ranck took over the "March of Events" section Hearst instructed him to make the section "interesting but impressive" in order to gain prestige for the papers. To this end Ranck sought articles or series by prominent world leaders and publication of memoirs or letters of statesmen of world renown such as William Borah, Winston Churchill, Calvin Coolidge, Edward Herriot, Benito Mussolini, Pope Pius XI, George Bernard Shaw, and Woodrow Wilson. The files contain correspondence concerning related negotiations and publication, but these letters are mainly between Ranck and other Hearst organization staff or literary agents. Seldom is there correspondence with the author. Folders 113-115 contain a few autographed manuscripts of articles.
There are many exchanges in the Hearst correspondence illustrating Hearst's concern for public morals and his interest in exposing the evils of Communism. The Beal files concern one such feature. Ranck's letters to Hearst occasionally concern the quality of the newspaper in the face of Depression era budget cuts.
Many of the other files relate to the Hearst chain's interest in securing and promoting stories involving expeditions to the Arctic and Antarctic and pioneering aeronautical flights. The largest file concerns the Hearst-funded expedition by Sir Hubert Wilkins to Antarctica and his later unsuccessful attempt to travel under the Arctic Sea in a submarine. Other files concern articles on the flight of the DoX zeppelin around the world; Umberto Nobile's plans to take an airship to the Arctic; the attempt by Polish flyers Idzikouski and Kubala to fly non-stop from Paris to New York; Commander Burney's proposal for a forty-eight hour airship route between London, New York, and Montreal; Roscoe Turner and Clyde Pangborn's entry in the Robertson international air race from London to Melbourne; and a flight by Roger Q. Williams and Lewis A. Yancey between New York and Rome.
The last folder in the papers includes a small quantity of Ranck's personal papers. These include a few letters, photographs of Mt. Ranck, an autographed manuscript of an Edwin Markham poem, and an obituary.
Biographical / Historical
Than Vanneman Ranck was born in Philadelphia in 1874. In 1896 he began his career as a reporter. He joined the Hearst newspapers as an editor in 1906. Ranck remained with the Hearst chain until his retirement in 1937, achieving the position of editorial manager for all the Hearst papers. He died in Easton, Maryland on July 30, 1947.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Aeronautics -- Flights; Journalism; Newspaper publishing; Voyages and travels; Antarctica -- Aerial exploration; Journalists; Hearst, William Randolph, 1863-1951; Knox, Frank, 1874-1944; Markham, Edwin, 1852-1940; Ranck, Than Vanneman, 1874-1947; Sarfatti, Margherita, 1880-1961; Wilkins, George H., Sir (George Hubert), 1888-1958
- Correspondence
  - Andrée expedition, 1930-1931, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
  - Beal, Fred E., 1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 8-11)
  - Berlin bureau, 1928-1931 (Box 1, Folder 12-19)
  - Berlin bureau, 1932-1935, undated (Box 2, Folder 20-30)
  - Borah, William E., 1928-1929, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Bowman, Isaiah, 1928-1931, undated (Box 2, Folder 32-34)
  - Churchill, Winston, 1930-1931, undated (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
  - Coolidge, Calvin, 1930-1931, undated (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
  - Coolidge, Grace Goodhue, 1929-1930, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Dornier DoX expedition, 1928-1929 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Dornier DoX expedition, 1930-1931, undated (Box 3, Folder 41-50)
  - Foreign statemen articles, 1930-1933, undated (Box 3, Folder 51-54)
  - Gandhi, Mahatma, 1931-1932, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Harbord, J. G., 1935, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Hearst, William Randolph, 1928-1932 (Box 4, Folder 57-73)
  - Hearst, William Randolph, 1933-1935 May (Box 5, Folder 74-89)
  - Hearst, William Randolph, 1935, June-1936 (Box 6, Folder 90-104)
  - Hearst, William Randolph, 1937, undated (Box 7, Folder 105-112)
  - Herriot, Edouard, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - Hillman, William, 1929-1932, undated (Box 7, Folder 114-115)
  - Joffre, Joseph Jacques Césaire, 1931, undated (Box 7, Folder 116)
  - Knox, Frank, 1928-1930, undated (Box 7, Folder 117-118)
  - Kreuger, Ivar, 1932, undated (Box 7, Folder 119)
  - London bureau, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 120-121)
  - London bureau, 1929-1937, undated (Box 8, Folder 122-140)
  - London bureau, undated (Box 9, Folder 141-145)
  - Mawson, Douglas, 1929-1930 (Box 9, Folder 146)
  - Mears, John Henry, 1928-1931 (Box 9, Folder 147-148)
  - Mussolini, Benito, 1930-1933, undated (Box 9, Folder 149-152)
  - Nobile, Umberto, 1928-1929 (Box 9, Folder 153-156)
  - Nobile, Umberto, undated (Box 10, Folder 157)
  - Painlevé, Paul, 1930-1931, undated (Box 10, Folder 158-159)
  - Pershing memoirs, 1930-1931 (Box 10, Folder 160)
  - Pignatelli, Valerio, 1930-1931 (Box 10, Folder 161)
  - Polish flyers, 1928-1929 (Box 10, Folder 162)
  - Pope Pius XI, 1929-1931, undated (Box 10, Folder 163-167)
  - Riisser-Larsen, Hjalmar, 1932-1933 (Box 10, Folder 168)
  - Rome bureau, 1928-1932 (Box 10, Folder 169-170)
  - Rome bureau, 1933-1935 (Box 11, Folder 171-172)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1932 (Box 11, Folder 173)
  - Sandino, Augustino, 1931 (Box 11, Folder 174)
  - Sarfatti, Marguerite G., 1929-1934 (Box 11, Folder 175-177)
  - Shaw, George Bernard, 1928 (Box 11, Folder 178-179)
  - Shearer, W. B., 1924-1932 (Box 11, Folder 180)
  - Stalin, Josef, undated (Box 11, Folder 181)
  - Transatlantic flight R-100, 1928-1930 (Box 11, Folder 182-183)
  - Tunney, Gene, undated (Box 11, Folder 184)
  - Turner-Pangborn, 1934-1935 (Box 12, Folder 185)
  - White, T. J., 1931-1937 (Box 12, Folder 186-188)
  - Wilkins, Sir Hubert, 1928-1931 March (Box 12, Folder 189-197)
  - Wilkins, Sir Hubert, 1931 March-1935, undated (Box 13, Folder 198-208)
  - Williams, Roger Q. and Lewis A. Yancey, 1928-1931 (Box 13, Folder 209-211)
  - Wilson, Woodrow, 1927-1935, undated (Box 13, Folder 212-216)
  - von Buelow memoirs, undated (Box 13, Folder 217)
  - von Huenefeld, Baron Ehrenfried Gunther, 1928 (Box 14, Folder 218)
  - von Wiegand, Karl, 1928-1929 June (Box 14, Folder 219-236)
  - von Wiegand, Karl, 1929 July-1932, undated (Box 15, Folder 237-250)
  - Personal, 1916-1947 (Box 15, Folder 251)